Preliminary Inventory to the George Davis Herron Papers, 1916-1927
Hoover Institution Archives
- BOUND VOLUMES (on shelf)
  - Volume VI. Italy
    - Herron to Sforza. Statement at London Conference on international application of the Lord's Prayer; its significance with regard to Italian state of mind, 1921 April 16 (Item LXXIII)
    - Herron to Karoly. Informing him that his books etc. will be returned through Senator Vigliani, 1921 April l18 (Item LXXIV)
    - Herron to Sforza. Acknowledging note about Count Karoly; notified him about Senator Vigliani, 1921 April 18 (Item LXXV)
    - Sforza to Herron. Answering to letter of 16th; giving his statement at the Conference of Rome on the welfare of one's neighbours, 1921 April 22 (Item LXXVI)
    - Karoly to Herron. Acknowledging receipt of letters of March 29th and April 18th; giving thanks for Herron's interest in his case; Prof. Granberg's kindness; asking for opinion as to advisability of returning to Italy to obtain rectification and where to establish himself and family; the need of men like Herron to uphold justice and social progress for humanity, 1921 May 9 (Item LXXVII)
    - Herron to Karoly. Replying to above; advising against Karoly's return to Italy; suggesting his taking refuge in England; Mazzini; Kropotkin; has sent a copy of his "The Defeat of Victory," 1921 May 20 (Item LXXVIII)
    - Herron to Sforza. Concerning his resignation from the Ministry for Foreign Affairs; Herron's sincere hope to the contrary; Giolitti's Government, 1921 May 20 (Item LXXIX)
    - Orsini to Herron. Acknowledging receipt of book; expressing concern about Herron's health. In Italian, 1921 May 24 (Item LXXX)
    - Sforza to Herron. Acknowledging letter of May 24th; interest in Herron's article, 1921 June 7 (Item LXXXI)
    - Ambassador de Martino to Herron. Conveying the sincere thanks of H.M. the King of Italy for "The Defeat in Victory," 1921 June 17 (Item LXXXII)
    - Herron to de Martino. Acknowledging above; His Majesty's kindness; Herron's appreciation of his decoration; meeting in Paris, 1921 June 25 (Item LXXXIII)
    - Herron to Sforza. Situation of Georgian students in Italy; their republic in the hands of the Bolshevists; failure of promised British help; Georgian faith in Italy; the help they need only to be temporary, 1921 July 19 (Item LXXXIV)
    - Herron to Sforza. Sending thanks for his parliamentary discourse on foreign affairs; regret that Sforza is no longer at the head of the Foreign Office; lack of moral value in meeting at Washington - merely an agreement of super-capitalists; England, America and Japan to divide China between them and France to be given free hand on the Continent; Italy must not fail; Herron's thought of returning to Florence to resume literary life; private family matters; book on Italy will appear in the early autumn; expressing good wishes, 1921 July 19 (Item LXXXV)
  - Volume VI. Italy and Serbia
    - Professor George D. Herron to Mr. Hugh R. Wilson for the State Department. Resentment and disappointment of Slav nations at pronouncements of Lloyd George and President Wilson; first interview with Yougo-Slav representatives describing their feelings that they had been sacrificed to the hope of a premature peace, giving some facts concerning the history of Serbia both during the war and previously; second interview with Yougo-Slav representatives, giving Herron's explanation of mistranslations in reports, and points in pronouncements which were in their favour; Dalmatian coast; possible union with Montenegro; hope of union with Bosnia, Herzegovina and Croatia, and establishment of League of Nations; interview with Boginoff of Czech Delegation; Bohemia ready to rise for Allies; her desire for independence; interview with Professor Wincenty Lutoslawsky of Polish Delegation, giving his view that Poland will be mutilated; demand for access to the sea; choice between Poland and Prussia, the greater part of Prussian population being Polish in origin; general desire of Slav nations for dismemberment of Austro-Hungarian Empire, extinction of Kingdom of Prussia and abolition of strategic frontiers, 1918 January 25 (Item I)
    - Herron to the American Legation. Appeal to America to intervene to obtain permission from England and France to send food to Serbia via Switzerland; giving brief information as to conditions in Serbia; precautions taken to prevent supplies reaching enemies, 1918 April 20 (Item II)
    - Herron to Dr. Woolston. Refusal of England and France to allow Swiss goods to be sent to Serbia; giving precautions taken to prevent goods reaching enemy hands and some ideas of the conditions in Serbia, 1918 September 26 (Item III)
    - Herron to State Department. Dr. Trumbic's first interview; questions at issue between Italy and Serbia and request for American intervention. Baron Sonnino's antipathy to Serbia and opposition to Austrian dismemberment; his dislike of American influence in Europe; Serbian objection to the Pact of London; German preparations for final offensive against Italy and need of American troops in Italy; can advantage be taken of military position to intervene on Serbia's behalf?; Trumbic's plan for the overthrow of Austria; his character, 1918 September 27 (Item IV)
    - Herron to State Department. Yougo-Slav and Czecho-Slovak terms of Armistice; Bolshevik peril east of the Rhine, 1918 November 2 (Item V)
    - Enclosure to the above, in French (Item V A)
    - Herron to State Department. "The New Nations and the Bolsheviki."; Political and historical characteristics of Czecho-Slovakia and their capacity for self-government; disappointment with Yougo-Slavs and the grasping attitude of all parties; Italian readiness to make sacrifices in favour of Serbia and Serbia's refusal to negotiate; her acceptance of Austrian navy; her action at meetings of seven nationalities in Geneva; trouble may be due to understanding between Pachitch and Sonnino; need for immediate action by America and Allies; Bolshevik dangers to European civilization, 1918 November 11 (Item VI)
    - Mr. W.G.M. Edward to Herron. Asking for memorandum on Yougo-Slavia and Italy and any communications for Sir Horace, 1918 November 14 (Item VII)
    - Professor Bergese on behalf of Orlando for Herron. Wire. Invitation to visit Rome; Trento, Trieste and Adriatic towns, 1918 November 16 (Item VIII)
    - Mr. S. Osusky to Herron. Complaining that letters are opened and giving this as the reason for not sending letter on Italy and Yougo-Slavia; acknowledging documents and quoting statement of Kurt Eisner; expecting to meet Herron at Peace Conference, 1918 November 26 (Item IX)
    - Marquis Paulucci di Calboli to Herron. Suggesting that Yougo-Slavia report should be sent to Balfour, 1918 November 25 (Item X)
    - Herron to Paulucci. Replying that report went to Balfour, Colonel House, American General Headquarters and Washington, 1918 November 27 (Item XI)
    - Herron to The President. Relations between Italy and Serbia; disappointments in Serbs; suggesting interview with Marquis Durezzo; unreliable pretensions of the Yougo-Slavs, 1919 March 17 (Item XII)
    - Sig. Battaglia to Herron. Communication to newspapers; interview with Kramer, 1919 April 10 (Item XIII)
    - Mr. A. Trumbic to Herron. Interview with "Agence Centrale" containing attacks on Yougo-Slavs; Koritza and Trieste; the Banat; Scutari; Serbian massacres with Italy, Roumania and Albania; Serbia's part in the war; relations with Austria; Adriatic question, 1919 April 14 (Item XIV)
    - Copy of interview mentioned in the above letter (Item XIV A)
    - Herron to The Hon. P.H. Stovall. Enclosing copy of article on Italy; expressing surprise at America's attitude towards her friends, 1919 April 25 (Item XV)
    - Herron to Paulucci. Enclosing copy of article on Italy; suggesting its publication in "L'Epoca," 1919 April 25 (Item XVI)
    - Paulucci to Herron. Acknowledging receipt of articles; correcting number of dead and wounded, 1919 April 25 (Item XVII)
    - Herron to Dulles. Enclosing copy of the following letter to The President, 1919 May 1 (Item XVIII)
    - Herron to The President. Enclosing copy of the following letter to Mr. Trumbic on the Yougo-Slav claims; mentioning that conversations with Orlando and Sonnino were reported to the Secretary of State; regretting lost opportunities, 1919 May 1. See The Peace - Dillon Document VII (Item XIX)
    - Herron to Mr. A. Trumbic. Replying to his letter of April 14th; interview with "Agence Centrale"; attack by Kramer; giving true account of interview; not a delegate to the Peace Commission; no influence with Wilson; no knowledge of his decisions; suggested solution of Balkan problem; issue between Wilson and Orlando; Peace not made on basis of Fourteen Principles; Italy misjudged; Seton-Watson and Wickham-Steed suggest compromise; Herron's appeals for Yougo-Slavia, 1919 May 1. See The Peace - Dillon Document VII (Item XX)
    - Herron to Stovall. Enclosing a copy of the above letter, 1919 May 1 (Item XXI)
    - Paulucci to Herron. Enclosing letter for Nobili; asking for details about Document XX, 1919 May 1 (Item XXII)
    - Herron to Paulucci. Enclosing copies of Documents XIV and XX, which he is at liberty to show to Sonnino and Orlando; interview of Yougo-Slav delegates, 1919 May 2 (Item XXIII)
    - Stovall to Herron. Acknowledging letters, 1919 May 5 (Item XXIV)
    - Herron to The Editor of The New York Herald. Published interviews; Herron's relations with the President; campaign Italy; civilization's debt to her, 1919 May 14 (Item XXV)
    - Herron to Mr. R.J. MacHugh. Returning letters; Mr. Trumbic and Yougo-Slavs; Dr. Dillon; "Daily Telegraph"; Miss Anderson, 1919 May 14. See Colonel MacHugh Document XI, Supplementary General Document IV (Item XXVI)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Urging Wilson to yield on Fiume question; danger of civil war in Italy and the Balkans, 1919 September 28 (Item XXVII)
    - Herron to Paulucci. Above letter to Colonel House, 1919 September 28 (Item XXVIII)
    - House to Herron. Acknowledging letter of 28th; feelings on world-wide situation, 1919 September 30 (Item XXIX)
    - Herron to Baron Acton. Intervention of the President in Italian questions; Vesnitch; France-Serbian military convention; Baron Sonnino's conciliatory attitude, 1920 February 19 (Item XXX)
  - Volume VI. Italy and Albania
    - Professor George D. Herron to Mr. Hugh Wilson. Albanian appeal for American protectorate; giving notes on history and national characteristics of Albanians; career and character of Dr. Adamidi, 1918 February 19 (Item I)
    - Dr. Adamidi Pasha to Herron. Enclosing report on Albanian rights and aspirations; proposed Greco-Albanian confederation to fight the Prussians of Mittel-Balkans, 1918 February 18 (Item II)
    - Enclosure in French to above (Item III)
    - Translation of Document III (Item IV)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Albanian objection to Italian military occupation and interference in education; desire for American occupation; objection to Serbian occupation of Kossovo and Monastir; Greek invasions of Epirus; Italian imperialism in Balkans, 1919 March 13 (Item V)
    - Herron to The President. Enclosing two memoranda from the Albanian National Committee; history and national characteristics of the Albanians, 1919 March 17 (Item VI)
    - Herron to Sir W. Tyrrell. Enclosing correspondence regarding Albania; suggested intervention of Mr. Vanderlip, 1919 March 18 (Item VII)
    - Herron to Tyrrell. Enclosing previous memorandum of the Albanian National Committee for the Prime Minister, 1919 March 19 (Item VIII)
    - Herron to The President. Same as previous document, 1919 March 19 (Item IX)
    - Adamidi to Lloyd George through Herron. Expressing gratitude to the British Government; appealing for protection; historical summary of Albania; revolt of 1908; Pact of London; Serbian retreat through Albania; Coitra, 1919 March 19 (Item X)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Enclosing appeal to The President; Republic of Koritza, 1919 March 20 (Item XI)
    - Adamidi to The President through Herron. Serbian and Greek attacks on Albania; Republic of Koritza; Italian claim to littoral; Minister Pachitch and Prince Regent Alexander; urgent appeal for American Protectorate, 1919 March 20 (Item XII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Communications forwarded as requested; reference to influences at work in Paris, 1919 March 21 (Item XIII)
    - Adamidi to The President through Herron. Invasion and claims of Serbs, Greeks, Austrians, Montenegrins and Italians; Pact of London; French occupation of Koritza; appeal for American protectorate; suggestion that Herron should be at the head of the Commission, 1919 March 21 (Item XIV)
    - Herron to Mr. H. Morley. Asking for copy of Document VIII, 1919 March 22 (Item XV)
    - Morley to Herron. Acknowledging above and promising to have copies made and sent, 1919 March 26 (Item XVI)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Asking for reply to petition to America; suggesting appeal to H.E. Morgenthau, 1919 March 29 (Item XVII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Replying to preceding letter; waiting for settlement of Adriatic question between Serbia and Italy; failure of Peace Conference; suggesting meeting with Mr. Stovall, 1919 March 30 (Item XVIII)
    - Herron to The President. Albanian National Committee anxious about future of Albania; enclosing Document XXIII, 1919 April 7 (Item XIX)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Same as above, 1919 April 7 (Item XX)
    - Herron to Sir W. Tyrrell. Same as above, 1919 April 7 (Item XXI)
    - Herron to Dillon. Forwarding omitted Albanian memorandum, 1919 April 15 (Item XXII)
    - Adamidi to The President through Herron. Expressing gratitude to American delegates; Koritza; referring to Brailsford's "Peace of the Balkans"; Pact of London a cause of the war; Albanian claim to Kissovo, Ipek, Dibia, Monastir; Serbia's deceit; help given to her during retreat; notes on history of Albania; appeal to America, 1919 April 7 (Item XXIII)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Request to be received by friends in Paris, 1919 April 30 (Item XXIV)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Above request forwarded to The President personally, 1919 May 1 (Item XXV)
    - Herron to The President. Request for interview on behalf of Dr. Adamidi, 1919 May 1 (Item XXVI)
    - Mr. G.F. Close, Confidential: Secretary to The President, to Herron. Granting above interview, 1919 May 6 (Item XXVII)
    - Herron to The President. Asking again for personal interview on behalf of Dr. Adamidi; notes on his career, 1919 May 30 (Item XXVIII)
    - Herron to Marquis Paulucci. Suggesting that Orlando and Sonnino should see Dr. Adamidi immediately on his arrival in Paris, 1919 May 30 (Item XXIX)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Regretting his illness; anxiety about Albanian question; offering to visit him, 1919 September 26 (Item XXX)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Enclosing following document, asking that it may be sent to Colonel House, Mr. Lodge and the Senate at Washington, 1919 October 2. See Roumanian Document XXIII pt. 2 (Item XXXI)
    - Enclosure to above. War in the Balkans imminent; pan-german agents; intrigues against Albania; Treaty of London 1913; terms satisfactory to Albania, 1919 October 1 (Item XXXI A)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Enclosing above, with notes on Dr. Adamidi's career and comments on the Balkan situation, 1919 October 3 (Item XXXII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Telling him that his memorandum has been sent to Colonel House and enclosing additional copies of it, 1919 October 3 (Item XXXIII)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Asking that memorandum be sent to the successor of Colonel House; also to friends in America, 1919 October 8 (Item XXXIV)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Assuring him that Colonel House received memorandum before leaving Paris; also laying the case of Albania before influential people in America; the President's recovery, 1919 October 8 (Item XXXV)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Mr. Tourtouli; Greeks threaten Koritza and inhabitants are in flight and preparing for revolution; asking for truth from American Delegation in Paris, 1919 October 8 (Item XXXVI)
    - Mr. A.W. Dulles to Herron. Stating that no decision has been come to with regard to Albania and Koritza; secretary from America, 1919 October 16 (Item XXXVII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Giving him the above information, 1919 October 20 (Item XXXVIII)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Appealing for defence before American and English governments, 1919 November 4 (Item XXXIX)
    - Adamidi to Herron. The President's vigorous defence of Albania against Lloyd George; repeated appeal for American support; Italian Socialists and Nitti, 1920 February 21 (Item XL)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Assuring him that everything possible has been done; rupture between The President and Colonel House healed; Serbia, rather than Italy Albania's enemy; Herron's breakdown, 1920 February 24 (Item XLI)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Asking for introduction in American for Mr. Cébrézi, 1920 March 25 (Item XLII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Going to Rome; letters sent to E. Rand and Colonel House; prospect poor; reaction against The President, 1920 March 26 (Item XLIII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Desiring to confer with Albania; conversation with Count Sforza, 1920 June 19 (Item XLIV)
    - Herron to Count Sforza. Albanian situation; Dr. Adamidi's career and position; Lord R. Cecil's secretary; position in House of Commons; postponement of meeting in Geneva; request of Albanian National Committee that Herron should mediate with Italy; President Giolitti and the Consulta; Albania's preparations for autonomy; their friendship for Italy; Valona; commercial and mineral exploitations; their determination to fight for independence; Italy's opportunity, 1920 June 21 (Item XLV)
    - Herron to Major Langley. Albanian situation; Greek concessions to International Tobacco Trust; French subsidies to Serbia; proposal to divide Albania between Serbia and Greece; Greek and Serbian incursions; Albanians incited against Italy, 1920 June 22 (Item XLVI)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Sufferings of Albanian prisoners taken by Italians; deliverance urgently needed, 1920 June 22 (Item XLVII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Replying to above; will give all help possible, 1920 June 23 (Item XLVIII)
    - Sforza to Herron. Acknowledging letter of June 18; declarations of Italian Prime Minister; on Albanian policy, 1920 July 7 (Item XLIX)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Asking for news of Albania; referring unfavourably to Baron Aliotti, 1920 July 17 (Item L)
    - Herron to Minister Orsini. Conference with Adamidi; his authority; possibility of French influence; her enmity toward Italy; Franco-American finance; the International Tobacco Trust; Vesnitch and Trumbic; France alarmed at Italy's attitude; English acquiescence in French intrigues against Italy; Yougo-Slav's despair at The President's valueless friendship; Italy's attitude correct; advising that she go to extreme of conciliation with Albania, 1920 July 19 (Item LI)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Albanian objection to Aliotti; Pact of London; determination to resist any attempt to divide Albania; Nitti and Tittoni; Sforza's intervention required, 1920 July 20 (Item LII)
    - Orsini to Herron. Acknowledging letter of July 19th which has been sent to Count Sforza, 1920 July 21 (Item LIII)
    - Sforza to Orsini. Telegram addressed to Orsini for Herron: Aliotti replaced by Manzoni, 1920 July 27 (Item LIV)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Asking for interview, 1920 July 28 (Item LV)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Rumour that Italian Government has repudiated agreement with Albania, 1920 July 29 (Item LVI)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Telegram to Villars sur Ollon. Urgent request for interview, 1920 July 30 (Item LVII)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Replying to letter of 29th that there is no truth to rumour; "Agence Centrale" being used by French Government against Italy; asking for immediate interview, 1920 July 30 (Item LVIII)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Telegram in answer to his; too ill to travel; asking for communication by letter, 1920 July 31 (Item LIX)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Acknowledging letter concerning Aliotti and Manzoni; Valona and Saseno; Albanian friendship for Italy, 1920 August 2 (Item LX)
    - Orsini to Herron. Acknowledging letter and invitation, 1920 August 3 (Item LXI)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Asking for Italian support of Albanian question at Paris through Count Sforza; Greek and Serbian claims, 1920 August 4 (Item LXII)
    - Orsini to Herron. Acknowledging letter from Adamidi; telegram to Sforza; Italian relations with Albania, 1920 August 10 (Item LXIII)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Serbian invasion into Albania, 1920 August 19 (Item LXIV)
    - Mr. Kees Boeke to Herron. Asking for interview in order to obtain information about Albania for the General Committee of the Movement towards a Christian International, 1920 September 24 (Item LXV)
    - Herron to Adamidi. Enclosing introduction to H.E. Attolico and Mrs. Bagg; Herron leaving for Italy, 1920 November 5 (Item LXVI)
    - Herron to H.E. Attolico. Introducing Dr. Adamidi; his desire to be connected with Ambassador Tittoni, 1920 November 5 (Item LXVI A)
    - Herron to Mrs. Bagg. Introducing Dr. Adamidi, 1920 November 5 (Item LXVI B)
    - Herron to Orsini. Informing him of Document LXVI, with request to notify Sforza, 1920 November 5 (Item LXVII)
    - Herron to Attolico. Informing him of Documents LXVI A and LXVII, 1920 November 5 (Item LXVIII)
    - Adamidi to Herron. Acknowledging Document LXVI; disappointment at Tittoni's refusal to receive Albanian Delegation, 1920 November 10 (Item LXIX)
  - Volume VII. Bulgaria
    - Herron to Mr. H.R. Wilson. Preface to Bulgaria. Interviews with Mr. Shipkoff; his position, career and character; his desire that America should not declare war on Bulgaria; acting as confidential ambassador of his King; Robert College and services of Dr. Washburn; Bulgaria owes her independence to America; effort to drive a mean bargain; Germany's offer to Bulgaria of Macedonia and the Dobrudja and part of Serbia; no encouragement from England and France; German power in Bulgaria and lands etc. occupied there by her; German soldiery treat these as a German conquest; Bulgaria's relations with Turkey; Allies should make Bulgaria the bulwark against German expansion; Hungary ready to join Bulgaria; Bulgaria cannot make an actual separate peace but would fulfill the substantial conditions; her prospect to possess the Balkans; her desire to bribe American capital; Shipkoff's inconsistent stories about Roumania and Salonica; program for Bulgarian Confederation of the Balkans; America would injur herself by war on Bulgaria; invitation to Herron to go to Bulgaria and offer of money for such; his opinion of position; Bulgaria scheming to obtain benefits from both sides; servile hypocrisy; Bulgaria ready to betray both sides, Allies and Central Empires; impossibility of accepting her offers from moral standpoint; would be betrayal of Serbia, Roumania and Greece; would release Bulgaria from consequences of her treacherous action, 1918 January 24 (Item I)
    - Herron to Mr. H.R. Wilson. Further interview with Mr. Shipkoff; he urges the cause of Austria; possibility of German influence through Mr. Meinl and Professor Lammasch; renewed invitation to Herron to visit Bulgaria; her intention to absorb the Balkan peninsula; enclosing petition from Dr. Adamidi, 1918 February 10 (Item II)
    - Herron from Dr. Adamidi. Enclosure to Document II. Bulgarian claims to Macedonia and Dobrudja; Albanian claim to independence; Bulgarian ill-treatment of Albanians; Bulgar's history; Albanian rights, undated (Item II A)
    - J.C. Crew to H.R. Wilson. The President's impression of Herron, 1918 February 19. Transferred to Between President Wilson and Herron, Document II (Item III)